Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection Archive
Rare Book and Special Collections Division, Library of Congress
Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection Archive 1913-2005 (bulk 1945-1990)
RB010001
Library of Congress. Rare Book and Special Collections Division
ca. 10,800 items (31 containers, 13 linear feet)
Rare Book and Special Collections Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Records of the collection of illustrated books acquired by Lessing J. Rosenwald and now held by the Library of Congress. Correspondence, Subject File, speeches and writing, printed ephemera, and miscellany related to the rare book collection and its creator, Lessing J. Rosenwald. Contains records of the Library of Congress's custodianship of the collection, administrative and legal documents, planning material for related exhibits and publications, and research files.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Fine, Ruth, 1941- --Correspondence.; Goff, Frederick Richmond, 1916-1982--Correspondence.; Hunt, Kathleen T.--Correspondence.; Matheson, William, 1927- --Correspondence.; Mongan, Elizabeth--Correspondence.; Rosenbach, A. S. W. (Abraham Simon Wolf), 1876-1952--Correspondence.; Rosenwald, Edith Goodkind--Correspondence.; Rosenwald, Lessing J. (Lessing Julius), 1891-1979, collector.; Rosenwald, Lessing J. (Lessing Julius), 1891-1979--Archives.; Rosenwald, Lessing J. (Lessing Julius), 1891-1979--Correspondence.; Rosenwald, Lessing J. (Lessing Julius), 1891-1979--Library.; Rosenwald, Lessing J. (Lessing Julius), 1891-1979.
Organizations
Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection (Library of Congress)--Archives.; Library of Congress. Rare Book and Special Collections Division.; Library of Congress. Rare Book and Special Collections Division.
Subjects
Book collecting--United States.; Book collectors--Archives.; Libraries--Special collections--Rare books.; Private libraries--United States.; Rare books--Collectors and collecting--United States.
Administrative Information
Provenance
The papers of Lessing J. Rosenwald were given to the Library of Congress by the Rosenwald estate between 1980 and 1983. The material was received by the Rare Book and Special Collections Division and the majority was transferred to the Manuscript Division where it was processed as the Lessing J. Rosenwald Papers. Some Rosenwald material was kept by the Rare Book and Special Collection Division and added to the Division's curatorial files. This archive of the collection was maintained by the Rare Book and Special Collection Division and described in 2010.
Related Material
See also the Lessing J. Rosenwald Papers held by the Manuscript Division.
Access and Restrictions
The archive of the Rosenwald Collection is open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Rare Book and Special Collections Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Scope and Content Note
The archive of the Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection documents the custodianship of this important collection of rare books by the Rare Book and Special Collections Division of the Library of Congress. In 1943, Rosenwald donated his print and rare book collections to the National Gallery of Art and the Library of Congress in Washington D.C. Having built a repository, Alverthorpe Gallery, at his estate in Jenkintown, Rosenwald retained physical custody of the collections during his lifetime, periodically transferring selections to Washington for exhibition, and ultimately giving 2,600 rare books and 5,000 reference books to the Library. After his death in 1979, Rosenwald's books were physically transferred to the Library of Congress and housed in the Rare Book and Special Collections Division.
Some material in the records originated with Rosenwald's own files at Alverthorpe, but the bulk of the material originated at the Library of Congress. The records were maintained by a number of different curators and administrators. Significant figures include Kathleen T. (Hunt) Mang, who served on Rosenwald's staff at Alverthorpe in the 1970s and later became the Curator of the Rosenwald Collection at the Library of Congress. Peter VanWingen replaced Mang as Rosenwald Curator in 1992. Chiefs of the Rare Book Division during this period include Frederick R. Goff (from 1945 to 1972) and William Matheson (from 1972 to 1987). At Alverthorpe, Rosenwald's print curators included Elizabeth Mongan (from 1937 to 1963) and Ruth Fine (from 1972 to 1980), both of whom later worked at the National Gallery of Art.
The Correspondence series contains letters concerning the collection between various administrators and curators, including Frederick R. Goff, Elizabeth Mongan, Kathleen T. Mang, and Rosenwald himself.
The Subject File contains administrative and legal information about the collection, including indentures and details about the 1980 transfer from Alverthorpe to the Library of Congress. It also contains records of various projects undertaken by the Library of Congress, including exhibitions of the collection, the construction of the Rosenwald memorial room, and the publication of the 1991 book, Vision of a Collector. In addition, the files contain research material about various individuals and books.
The Speeches and Writings File contains articles and speeches written by Rosenwald.
The Miscellany series contains press clippings and publications, miscellaneous ephemera, and speeches and writings by others. The writings by others section consists mainly of offprints and scholarly articles sent to Rosenwald, many inscribed with notes from the authors.
The Printed Ephemera series contains material produced by various printers, publishers, artists, booksellers, libraries, and bibliographic societies. Many of the items are mailings sent out by private presses such as the Gehenna Press and the Nonesuch Press. The series includes many book prospectuses, some of which are directly linked to items in the Rosenwald Collection.
The Oversize series contains material removed from other series and folders due to its size.
Arrangement of the Records
This collection is arranged in 6 series:
Correspondence, 1922-1990
Subject File, 1923-2005
Speeches and Writings File, 1945-1973
Miscellany, 1919-1991
Printed Ephemera, 1929-1988
Oversize, 1913-1979
http://lccn.loc.gov/2012657300
Container List
- Correspondence, 1922-1990 (Box 1-2)
  Letters received and copies of letters sent, memoranda, and miscellaneous enclosures.
  Arranged alphabetically by primary correspondent's name.
  - Goff, Frederick R., 1950-1953 (Box 1)
  - Lawler, Percy E., 1922-1927
  - Mang, Kathleen T., 1978-1990, n.d.
  - Mongan, Elizabeth, 1951-1956
  - Rennette, Baron de, 1979
  - Rosenwald, Edith, 1980-1989
  - Rosenwald, Lessing, J. See also Oversize
    - 1931-1950, (3 folders)
    - 1951-1977, (4 folders) (Box 2)
- Subject File, 1923-2005 (Box 2-15)
  Correspondence, miscellaneous enclosures, memoranda, administrative papers, bibliographies, printed matter, notes, working papers, articles, newspaper clippings, and financial and legal documents.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Acquisitions, 1979, 1989, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Acquisitions report, Rosenwald II, n.d., (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Additions, 1947-1954, n.d.
  - Alice manuscript, 1952-1954, n.d.
  - Alverthorpe Gallery, n.d.
  - Arenberg collection, 1955-1984, n.d.
  - Artists' books, 1984-1990, n.d.
  - Awards, 1982-1987, n.d.
  - Bibliographies by subject, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Binders, 1982
  - Blake requests, 1980-1984, n.d.
  - Blake, William, 1944-1984
  - Book descriptions and notes, n.d.
  - Books requested from Jenkintown, 1948-1955
  - Books returned to Jenkintown, 1944-1955, n.d.
  - Catalog errors, n.d. (Box 5)
  - Champfleury, 1987, n.d.
  - Clemente, Francesco, Departure of the Argonaut, Petersburg Press, 1985
  - Coe, Sue, Narcissism and Death, n.d.
  - Concordance between Rosenwald numbers and LJR numbers, n.d.
  - Council of Scholars, 1983
  - Doctrina Christiana, 1946-1948
  - Duplicate exchanges, 1980-1983, n.d.
  - Duplicate sales and books purchased from sale proceeds, 1968-1983
  - Exhibits
    - Agnes Etherington Art Centre, "Maurice Denis: Illustrator," 1982-1983
    - Alverthorpe, 1962
    - Alverthorpe, Association Internationale de Bibliophilie, 1971
    - American Institute of Graphic Arts, "The Early Illustrated Book," 1983
    - American Institute of Graphic Arts, meeting-symposium, n.d.
    - Archer M. Huntington Art Gallery, "Nuremberg: A Renaissance," 1981-1982
    - "Early Printed Books of the Low Countries," 1960-1963, n.d., (3 folders) (Box 6)
    - Fogg Art Museum, Blake exhibition, 1930-1931
    - Fogg Art Museum, early book illustrations, 1931-1932
    - Fraunces Tavern Museum, "For the Entertainment of Friends and Strangers," 1982
    - The Grolier Club, "100 Books Famous in Science," 1958
    - The Grolier Club, Venetian books, 1983
    - The Grolier Club, Spanish books, 1932-1933
    - Helen Foresman Spencer Museum of Art, "The Medieval Garden," 1982
    - Library of Congress, 1943
    - Library of Congress, 1945, (2 folders)
    - Library of Congress, 1947, (2 folders)
    - Library of Congress, 1948, (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - Library of Congress, 1955
    - Library of Congress, n.d.
    - Library of Congress, "Fresh Faces," 1980
    - Library of Congress, Giant Bible of Mainz, 1951-1952, (3 folders)
    - Library of Congress, "Heavenly Craft," 2004-2005
    - Library of Congress, librarian's case, 1984
    - Library of Congress, "Printed on Vellum," 1977, (2 folders)
    - Library of Congress, Rosenwald's 88th birthday, 1979 (Box 8)
    - Library of Congress, "Theater of the Whole World," 1982
    - Library of Congress, "Treasures from the Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection," 1973, (2 folders)
    - Lisbon, "The Portuguese Discoveries and Renaissance Europe," 1981
    - Museum of Fine Arts, Springfield, Mass., "Glorious Horsemen," 1981-1982
    - National Arts Club, Goudy exhibit, 1934
    - National Gallery of Art, Giovanni Battista Piazzetta exhibit, 1982
    - Philadelphia Community College, "The Graphic Image," 1980
    - Print Council of America, "Treasures from the Rosenwald Collection," 1979
    - Rosenbach Museum and Library, "Rosenwald and Rosenbach: Two Philadelphia Bookmen"
      - Catalog drafts, n.d., (2 folders)
      - Catalog proofs, n.d. (Box 9)
      - Correspondence, 1982-1983
      - Insurance, 1983
      - "The Philadelphia Connection" drafts, 1983-1984
      - Rosenbach research material, 1923-1965
      - Selection list, n.d.
    - Yale Center for British Art, "Blake in Context," 1981-1982
  - Facsimiles, 1944-1984, (3 folders)
  - The Fleuron, 1927-1929, n.d.
  - Folios, n.d.
  - Goff, Frederick, 1972-1983, n.d.
  - Grolier Club catalog, n.d.
  - Hinman collator, 1952-1964
  - Indentures (Box 10)
    - Correspondence, 1943-1979
    - Indentures, 1943-1980, (5 folders)
  - Levis Collection, 1977
  - Madison Council, n.d.
  - Mainz Psalter of 1457, 1948
  - Manuscripts, 1979-1982
  - Memo orders to Jenkintown, 1951-1953
  - Memos, 1981-1983
  - Memorial room, 1979-1992
  - Move from Alverthorpe to Library of Congress (Box 11)
    - Correspondence, 1943-1979
    - Inventory by crate, n.d.
    - Self map with crate numbers, n.d.
    - Shipment lists, n.d., (3 folders)
  - Office of Price Administration, 1941
  - Permanent storage, 1957-1976
  - Photocopies from files at Jenkintown, 1928-1941, n.d. (Box 12)
  - Policy Planning Committee, 1940-1947
  - Rare books not given, 1964-1979, n.d.
  - Rosenbach, A.S.W., 1927-1941, n.d.
  - Rosenwald catalog, 1952-1960
  - Rosenwald fund, 1989-1990, n.d.
  - Rosenwald, Julius, 1929-1976
  - Rosenwald, Lessing J., 1954-1979
  - Rosenwald Papers, Manuscript Division, 1981-1983, n.d., (2 folders)
  - Rosenwald scholar, 1988-1990
  - Rosenwald schools, n.d.
  - Rosenwald Symposium (Box 13)
    - Correspondence, 1978-1980
    - Publication, 1981
    - Abstract, 1980
  - Vision of a Collector
    - Book descriptions from catalog, n.d.
    - Contracts, 1987-1989
    - Contributor bios and addresses, n.d., (2 folders)
    - Contributor letters, 1987
    - Contributor letters, 1988 (Box 14)
    - Correspondence, 1986-1992, (4 folders)
    - Essays, n.d.
    - Exhibit, 1989-1990
    - Financials, 1988-1992, n.d.
    - Index, 1991-1992, n.d.
    - Planning notes and drafts, n.d.
    - Proposal, n.d.
    - Prospectus, n.d. (Box 15)
    - Publisher, 1987-1992, n.d.
    - Regular edition, 1991-1992, n.d.
    - Reviews, 1991-1992
  - War Production Board, 1942-1943 See also Oversize, (2 folders)
- Speeches and Writings File, 1945-1973 (Box 15)
  Photocopies of handwritten and typewritten drafts, printed copies, and miscellany relating to articles and speeches by Rosenwald.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material and therein by title.
  - Articles (Box 15)
    - "Credo of an American Jew," Issues, vol 17, no 9, 1963
    - "Formation of the Rosenwald Collection," Quarterly Journal, vol 3, no 1, October 1945
    - "Reminiscences of a Print Collector," American Scholar, 1973
    - "Story of an Unusual Purchase at Sotherby's," To Doctor R., 1946
  - Speeches
    - "Experiences in Collecting," Gleeson Library Associates dinner, May 2, 1971
    - Funeral of A.S.W. Rosenbach, July 3, 1952
    - National Gallery of Art, April 17, 1950
    - Philobiblon Club, October 18, 1956
    - "Responsibilities of a Collector," Artists Equity Association award dinner, April 12, 1961
- Miscellany, 1919-1991 (Box 16-23)
  Articles, newspaper clippings, programs, catalogs, cards, awards, certificates, honorary degrees, and speeches and writings by others.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material.
  - Articles about the Rosenwald Collection, 1943-1984, n.d., (2 folders) (Box 16)
  - Awards and honors to Rosenwald, 1928-1976 See also Oversize, (2 folders)
  - Dealer and auction catalogs
    - 1930-1972, (3 folders)
    - 1975-1981, n.d., (2 folders) (Box 17)
  - Exhibition programs, 1934-1940, n.d.
  - Gift book, Rosenwald birthday, 1961
  - Honorary Degrees See also Oversize
    - 1947-1966, (5 folders)
    - 1967-1969, (2 folders) (Box 18)
  - Library of Congress Information Bulletin, 1979-1991
  - Library of Congress Quarterly Journal, 1945-1965
  - Navy Discharge Papers, 1919
  - Newspaper clippings, 1943-1983, n.d., (2 folders)
  - Phone Directories, Sears, Roebuck and Co., 1944, n.d.
  - Press releases, 1943-1979 (Box 19)
  - Rosenwald bookplates, 1931, n.d.
  - Rosenwald holiday cards, 1947-1973, n.d.
  - Speeches by others
    - Collector's Club, Washington, March 16, 1951
    - Goff, Frederick, "Rosenwald and the Gift to a Nation," 1981
    - Matheson, William, "Lessing J. Rosenwald: A Great Book Collector," n.d.
    - Matheson, William, n.d.
    - VanWingen, Peter, Wichita State University Special Collections Department, 1981
  - Writings by others
    - Abrahams, Harold J., 1968-1971
    - Adams, Thomas R., 1954
    - Adelman, Seymour, 1945
    - Adhémar, Jean, 1960
    - Alexander-Jackson, Eleanor, 1970
    - Bagrow, Leo, 1951
    - Belt, Elmer, 1965
    - Boxer, C.R., 1950
    - Boyd, Julian P., 1947
    - Brown, Lloyd A., 1953
    - Chalmers, Anne Palms, 1969
    - Chalmers, John P., 1977
    - Chapon, François, 1974
    - Chartier, Roger, 1988
    - Chayes, Irene H., 1982-1984
    - Crompton, Robert D., 1963
    - David, Charles W., 1957
    - Donati, Lamberto, 1952
    - Drake, Stillman, 1978
    - Escoubé, Lucienne, 1980
    - Field, Richard S., 1969
    - Fine, Ruth, 1976-1982, n.d. (Box 20)
    - Fleming, John, 1946
    - Fordham, Jefferson R., 1971
    - Fontaine Verwey, Herman de la, 1980
    - Friedman, Lee M., 1947
    - Garvey, Eleanor M., n.d.
    - Goff, Frederick R. 1947-1981, (3 folder)
    - Green, Otis H., 1948
    - Griffiths, Antony, 1984
    - Gwinn, David Marshall, 1950
    - Hartz, Sem L., 1974
    - Harrsen, Meta, 1960
    - Heil, Walter, 1969
    - Hinman, Charlton, 1953-1954
    - Hodnett, Edward, 1978
    - Hofer, Philip, 1948
    - Hunter, Richard A., 1959
    - Jackson, William A., 1938-1951
    - Keesman, Wilma, 1982-1983
    - Kramer, Samuel Noah, 1944-1949 (Box 21)
    - Kraus, T. Peter, 1984
    - Krivatsy, Peter, 1968
    - Kronenberg, M. E., 1964
    - Lester, John A., 1958
    - Liebaers, Herman, 1965
    - Livingston, Virginia Wuerthele-Caspe, 1957
    - Marrow, James, 1978
    - Mayor, A. Hyatt, 1947
    - McManaway, James G., 1948-1951, n.d.
    - Minott, Charles I., 1979
    - Mongan, Agnes, 1949
    - Needham, Paul, 1985
    - O'Malley, Charles D., 1951-1953
    - Pächt, Otto, n.d.
    - Payne, John R., 1957
    - Penrose, Boies, 1961
    - Pingree, Isabelle, 1977
    - Pleij, Herman, 1982
    - Powell, Lawrence Clark, 1950
    - Reich, Nathaniel Julius, [1936]
    - Reichmann, Felix, 1945
    - Reilly, Bernard F., 1974
    - Roman, Gail Harrison, [1980]
    - Rosenbach, A.S.W., 1935-1939
    - Rosenthal, Erwin, 1967
    - Roth, Cecil, 1960 (Box 22)
    - Savin, Marion B., 1958-1959
    - Scaglia, Gustina, 1966
    - Schullian, Dorothy M., 1958
    - Setton, Kenneth M., 1956
    - Shepard, Katharine, 1969
    - Shipton, Clifford K., 1963
    - Strachan, Walter John, 1978-1981
    - Tobias, Channing H., 1957
    - Turner, Decherd, 1969
    - Turner, Justin G., 1956
    - Van Der Loon, P., 1966
    - Van Krimpen, H., [1951]
    - Vittorini, Domenico, 1953-1954, n.d.
    - Walton, Francis R., 1964-1971
    - Williams Jr., Franklin B., 1957
    - Winkler, Friedrich, 1958
    - Wolf 2nd, Edwin, 1950-1959, (2 folders)
    - Wolf, Thomas, 1974 (Box 23)
    - Wright, Austin T., 1930
    - Wright, Louis B., 1948
    - Wyllie, John Cook, n.d.
    - Wynne, Marjorie Gray, 1955
    - Zeitlin, Jake, 1960
- Printed Ephemera, 1929-1988 (Box 23-24)
  Prospectuses, catalogs, leaflets, booklets, cards, posters, keepsakes, programs, newsletters, and newspaper clippings.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of person or organization.
  - Allen Press, 1964 (Box 23)
  - American Philosophical Society, 1974
  - Arts et Métiers Graphiques, 1939
  - Baltazar, Julius, 1987-1988
  - Berliner, Harold, n.d.
  - Bibliophile Society, 1934, n.d.
  - Bird and Bull Press, 1967-1982
  - Book Club of California, 1937-1962
  - Book Collector's Packet, 1933
  - Boston Public Library, 1974
  - Broadside Press, 1936
  - Charles Breyner Art Publications, 1950
  - Cummington Press, 1951-1976
  - Dahlstrom, Grant, 1961-1977
  - Eberhardt, Fritz and Trudi, n.d.
  - Edward Stern and Company, n.d.
  - Far Gallery, 1963
  - Friends of the Harvard Library, n.d.
  - Gehenna Press, 1967-1975, n.d.
  - Gleeson Library Associates, 1975-1978
  - Godine, David, 1970
  - Golden Eagle Books, 1938-1939
  - Grabhorn Press, 1941-1973, n.d.
  - Gravesend Press, n.d.
  - Grolier Club, 1931-1972
  - Heron Press, 1971
  - Hofer, Philip, 1958
  - Hunt Botanical Library, 1958-1963
  - John Roberts Press, n.d.
  - Kaldewey Press, n.d.
  - Koch, Theodore Wesley, 1929-1931 (Box 24)
  - Lakeside Press, 1950
  - Lecuire, Pierre, 1974-1988, n.d.
  - Marion Press, 1943
  - Mayakovsky, Vladimir, 1973
  - Midday Club, 1955
  - Moncure Biddle and Company, 1938
  - Molehill Press, n.d.
  - Nash, John Henry, 1932-1936, n.d.
  - New Pyramid Press, 1984
  - Newberry Library Associates, 1973
  - Nonesuch Press, 1939
  - Orion Press, 1967
  - Overbrook Press, 1954-1961, n.d. See also Oversize
  - Peter Pauper Press, 1938, n.d.
  - Press of A. Colish, n.d.
  - Press of the Woolly Whale, 1932-1938, n.d.
  - Prairie Press, n.d.
  - Pynson Printers, 1935
  - Rampant Lions Press, 1979
  - Rogers, Bruce, 1953-1957
  - Shahn, Ben, 1959
  - Society of Bibliophiles, 1973
  - Stone, Reynolds, 1950
  - Tiessen, Wolfgang, n.d.
  - Trianon Press, 1957-1983
  - Typophiles, 1943-1966, n.d., (2 folders)
  - Unidentified, 1938-1969, n.d.
  - University of Chicago Library, 1970
  - University of Kentucky Library Associates, 1963
  - University of Virginia Library, 1956-1976
  - Volas, Barbara, n.d.
  - Wells College, Department of Fine Arts, 1942
  - Wilson, Adrian, 1956, n.d. See also Oversize
  - Wroth, Lawrence C., 1951
- Oversize, 1913-1979 (Box OV 1-OV 7)
  Arranged and described according to type of material or the series, containers, and folders from which the items were removed.
  - Correspondence (Box OV 1)
    - Rosenwald, Lessing J., 1964, n.d. (Box 1 and 2)
  - Subject File
    - War Production Board, 1942 (Box 14)
  - Miscellany
    - Awards and honors to Rosenwald (Box 15)
      - 1913-1979, (9 folders)
      - Matted certificates, 1959-1979 (Box OV 2)
    - Honorary Degrees, 1913-1979 (Box 16) (Box OV 3)
  - Printed Ephemera
    - American Autograph Shop, 1942
    - Hertzog, Carl, 1949
    - James Ford Bell Library, 1972
    - Jonquières, Henri, 1950
    - Maggs Bros., [1952]
    - Overbrook Press, 1952 n.d. (Box 23)
    - Wilson, Adrian, 1953-1955 (Box 23)
  - Photographs 1940-1970, n.d., (34 folders) (Box OV 4-5)
  - Plaques and medals, 1961-1971, n.d. (Box OV 6-7)